Guide to the People's Educational Camp Society and Camp Tamiment Photographs PHOTOS.155
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
People's Educational Camp Society and Camp Tamiment Photographs
1920s-1960s, (Bulk 1940s-1950s)
1940-1960
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
People's Educational Camp Society
Tamiment Library
Nimberger, Carol
Tishler, Anne
PHOTOS.155
1.75 Linear Feet
Camp Tamiment, a summer resort for socialists and their families, in near Bushkill, Pennsylvania, opened in 1921. Its purpose was to serve as a summer retreat for faculty, students, and friends of the Rand School of Social Science (a school for workers in New York City that was closely allied with the Socialist Party) and to provide a reliable source of revenue for the School. The Camp was also home to the Tamiment Playhouse, which became a major creative outlet for theater, dance, film, and television in the United States, nurturing major entertainment figures such as Danny Kaye. The Camp was a financial success from its outset, and had served as a major source of support for the Rand School for more than twenty years, when the Internal Revenue Service revoked the Camp's tax-exempt status in 1963. This action contributed directly to the Camp's demise; it closed in 1965 and was sold to commercial interests. The collection documents Camp buildings, facilities, and layout, and includes numerous portraits of Camp management, staff, and prominent guests. A significant number of the photographs are black and white postcards shot by two photographers Lewis "Snappy" Goren and Seymour Fischer for Camp guests and for the Camp itself.
(ca. 2,300 items); 8 x 10, 5 x 7, and 2 x 3 black and white photographs; black and white negatives.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials in this collection have been compiled by the Tamiment Library. These photographs were separated from related manuscript collections in the in Tamiment Library and gathered together to form an artificial collection. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 1963.001, NPA.2005.031, and NPA.2001.104.
Photographs were donated by Carol Nimberger, daughter of Arthur Rosenberg, in 2008. Films and video were donated by Anne Tishler in 2000. The accession number associated with these gifts is 2018.017.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Camp Tamiment, a summer resort for socialists and their families, near Bushkill, Pennsylvania, on Lake Tamiment, in the Pocono Mountains, opened in the summer of 1921. Bordering the grounds of Unity House (the resort run by the International Ladies Garment Workers Union, which had opened the previous year), the Camp was the brainchild of Mrs. Bertha Mailly, Executive Secretary of the Rand School of Social Science (a school for workers in New York City that was closely allied with the Socialist Party). It was founded for two purposes: to serve as a summer retreat--with educational and cultural offerings as well as recreation--for faculty, students, and friends of the School, and to provide a reliable source of revenue for the School. It was owned and operated by The People's Educational Camp Society (PECS), a corporation created by the School for the sole purpose of administering the Camp.
By the late1920s the Camp, which was intended for adults, came to include a bungalow colony, "Sandyville," on the same grounds, that housed families. It also was home to a theater, the Tamiment Playhouse, which became a major creative outlet for theater, dance, film, and television of the mid-twentieth century--in particular comedy. Actors such as Danny Kaye, Dick Shawn, Bea Arthur, Imogene Coca, and Carol Burnett, director and producer Max L. Liebman, choreographers and dancers such as Jerome Robbins and Anita Alvarez, and writers Woody Allen and Neil Simon are a small sample of the major entertainment figures nurtured at Camp Tamiment.
When it opened, the Camp was heralded as the "largest summer school and camp for workers in the world." But though summer classes were held at the Camp through the 1930s, they steadily lost their popularity as an attraction. Increasingly the Camp drew a more middle-class clientele and came to resemble a mainstream resort.
From its beginning Camp Tamiment was a successful--and profitable--enterprise. Indeed, it was able to provide the majority of the Rand School's financial support between 1937 and 1956. But Tamiment's success may have also been its downfall, for it attracted the attention of the Internal Revenue Service, which revoked the Camp's tax exempt status in 1963. This action contributed directly to the Camp's demise; two years afterwards it closed its doors and was sold to commercial interests. The Rand School, deprived of its major source of income, also folded soon thereafter.
Sources:
Martha LoMonoco. Every Week a Broadway Review, The Tamiment Playhouse, 1921-1960 (1992: Greenwood Press).
Squeri, Lawrence. Better in the Poconos: The Story of Pennsylvania's Vacationland (2002, Pennsylvania University Press).
Scope and Content Note
The collection documents in considerable detail the Camp buildings (interiors and exteriors), facilities, and its layout (including aerial shots).
A significant number of the photographs in this collection are black and white postcards shot by two "official" Camp Tamiment photographersCLewis "Snappy" Goren and Seymour Fischer. Their names appear on the postcards along with the year the photograps were shot. Some of these postcards appear to have been produced "on demand" for a fee, for guests at the Camp, to take home as souvenirs, while others seem to have been shot to record Camp life, Camp events (including performances at the Tamiment Playhouse), Camp directors and management (among them Bertha Mailly and Ben Josephson), staff (kitchen and athletic) and prominent guests. At least one of these photographers Lewis Goren was in residence at the Camp every summer, for more than a decade. Goren and Seymour Fischer (who, as far as is known, did not work together) also shot promotional photographs of the Camp that were used in its advertising and brochures; this work is also represented in the collection. Other photographers' work in the collection includes that of Ezra Stoller.
Arrangement
Chronological series is arranged by year and decade; topical series is arranged alphabetically.
Organized into 2 series:
Missing Title
I, Chronological
II, Topical
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Playhouse Photographs (Photographs 041)
People's Educational Camp Society Records (Tamiment 007.4)
Rand School of Social Science Records (Tamiment 007)
Ben Josephson Papers (Tamiment 084)
Tamiment Playhouse Records (Tamiment 107)
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu, (212) 998-2630 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Transparencies.; Color photographs.; Black-and-white negatives.; Black-and-white photographs.; Lake Tamiment (Pa.).; Pocono Mountains (Pa.).; Bushkill (Pa.); Summer resorts |z Pennsylvania |v Pictorial works.; Socialists |z United States |x Recreation |v Pictorial works.; Josephson, Ben, 1895-1980 -- |v Portraits; Mailly, Bertha -- |v Portraits; Stoller, Ezra.; Fischer, Seymour.; Goren, Lewis M.; Camp Tamiment (Pa.); People's Educational Camp Society; Nimberger, Carol; Tishler, Anne
- Series I: Chronological
  - 1920s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1920s[?], ca.1920s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1933 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1934 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1935 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1936 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1937 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1939 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1930s?, ca.1930s (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1940s (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1940s?, ca.1940s (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1940 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1941 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1942 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 1946 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 1947 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 1948 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1949 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 1950s (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - 1950s?, ca.1950s (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - 1950 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - 1952 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - 1953 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - 1955 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - 1956 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - CIO and AFL Luncheon at Clubhouse, Aug 8, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - 1957 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - 1958 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Eighth Annual Danny Kaye Golf Tournament, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - 1959 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - 1960 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - 1961 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - 1962 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - 1963 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - 1964 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - 1960s?, ca. 1960s (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Camp Tamiment Picture Postcards and Illustrated Brochures, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Negatives: 1940s?; 1948, ca.1940s (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Negatives: 1930s? 1940s?, ca.1930s- 1940s (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Series II: Topics
  - Aerial Shots, undated (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Ben Josephson Award, undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Buildings and Grounds, undated (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Buildings and Grounds—Clubhouse, undated (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Buildings and Grounds—Construction of, undated (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Buildings and Grounds—Construction of –General, undated (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Buildings and Grounds—Construction of—Golf Course—Hole #14, undated (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Buildings and Grounds—Lake Views, undated (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Buildings and Grounds—Laundry Room, undated (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Buildings and Grounds—Prints, Drawings and Architectural Renderings, undated (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Buildings—Interiors, undated (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Bus Stop, undated (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Conference, 1949, undated (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Hillquit Memorial, undated (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Performances, undated (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Portraits, undated (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Portraits—including Bertha Mailly and Ben Josephson, undated (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Promotional Materials, undated (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Recreation and Activities, undated (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Recreation and Activities--Golfers, undated (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - Scenic Views with Campers, undated (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - Staff, undated (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Tamiment Forum, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - Tamiment Forum, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - Tamiment Meetings and Lectures at Camp Tamiment (dated), undated (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - Tamiment Meetings and Lectures at Camp Tamiment (undated) (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - Tamiment Social and Economic Institute—Book Award, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - Unidentified, undated (Box 5, Folder 68)
  - Camp Tamiment photographs by Arthur Rosenberg, group photos, postcards, brochure, 1925-1950 (Box 6, Folder 1-6)
  - Camp Tamiment audiovisual materials, 1940-1952 (Box 7)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact Tamiment Library with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
- Unprocessed
  - Glass negatives (Box 1)